[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's say somebody has come to terms with the fact that they need to keep the precepts and be celibate if they want to get the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they still struggle to understand what they're supposed to, quote-unquote, do as a practice, if not meditate, in the modern sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the precepts obviously don't tell you what to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a list of things to not do, and once you no longer do those things, you still have all this time left.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you describe the practice for such a person?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they already described it, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Precepts are about the things that you won't do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you need to protect that for as long as your main mode of doing is concerned not about what do I do, but about what is it that I don't do and what I won't do, regardless of what comes my way.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it means being established in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does not mean I learned the precepts and kept them religiously for so long.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means, basically, my values have shifted in a sense that it doesn't matter what happens to me, what experience occurs, novelty, pleasant, unpleasant, doubtful.
[SPEAKER_01]: I might well not know what to do, what to say, how to react, but I will know what not to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I have no doubt about that, because I've been purifying that beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, when you take on the precepts, yes, you take them on by body, you take them on through the external form, but the whole point is, so that you can implement them on the mental level.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, killing, stealing, celibacy, non-celibacy, all these things, basically, you take on these precepts, and then, yes, you stop engaging with those things with the body, but then,
[SPEAKER_01]: How's your mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you revolve around it, like, throughout your day, thinking hateful thoughts, feeding them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, but I'm not killing anybody, but I'm wishing I could, or I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I'm withdrawn physically, but do I allow my mind to wallow and fantasize about stuff?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, oh, I should really upgrade that and not allow it on that level, because that's where the physical restraint is supposed to lead to.
[SPEAKER_01]: You confining your mind within the beneficial behaviors.
[SPEAKER_01]: All while dampening and refraining from giving in to the pressuring tendency to do something about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: To do something about a practice, to meditate.
[SPEAKER_00]: But surely I must do something palpable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all of that is just perpetuation of your own craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that is the sīla bhārata pāramāsa.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter if it's concerned with sīla or with duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: My duty is to meditate.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, your duty is to understand the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever people in the suttas meditate, monks meditate, when they translate that, again, colored with the contemporary Theravāda views of watch your nostrils and focus three feet in front of you and squint through your eyes, as if these things are relevant to anything or anyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever they say meditate, that's what they kind of like to imply.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when the suttas say meditate, they mean, like, go on and clarify things that are not clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are you still subject to suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are you taking things as yours that cause you to suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why can you not withdraw from sensuality?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are you still relishing the pleasure that can be obtained through your body?
[SPEAKER_01]: There's, like, myriad of aspects and options you could contemplate every single day, you could meditate on every single day.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, a monk goes... sickness, aging, death, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, a monk goes to an empty hut, says, as this hut is empty of others, so is this experience empty of the owner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, what meditation technique is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not an empty visualization, how Visuddhimagga tries to present it, just think these images in clay disks and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's genuinely like, this experience, here and now, it's empty of an owner.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have a sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not denying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that sense of ownership cannot be mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, that's not necessarily hard to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: People can wrap their head around.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, whether it will land on a dimension where it matters or not, well, that depends whether their behavior has been purified beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have... they've withdrawn themselves from sensuality from the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the basic satipaṭṭhāna, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: These contemplations in regard to the body, feeling, mind, that's what satipaṭṭhāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha says it's the one way only that leads to the purification of being, that leads to fulfillment of the seven enlightenment factors, fulfillment of mindfulness, fulfillment of the dhamma, dhammavicaya, fulfillment of the energy and everything else, fulfillment of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like samādhi, as in a state of composure that comes on the basis of pasādhi and calm, is the result of clearly delineating non-ownership, letting go, valsagā, the abandoning of the five hindrances, and all of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And actually, there are suttas that says a monk abandons the five, well, gradual trains, withdrawals from sensuality, all of that, and then abandons the hindrances, and then can practice satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: To bring all these things to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_01]: But generally, this is completely, as I said, yeah, but I must do something beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, to be fair, as I said, most of the, if not all of the Theravada world today, it is presenting it that way, because that's even how the Visuddhimāga originally presented it.
[SPEAKER_01]: All these corruptions could be traced back to those commentaries, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereby it's like, no, no, no, it doesn't matter the basis, doesn't matter which you are, just keep stabbing in the dark, and just keep doing these things randomly,
[SPEAKER_01]: Practice the sensation watching, calming, visualizations, practices and stuff, stuff, stuff, and sort of, kind of, make them sound like they come from the suttas, and then it will happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, again, you read the suttas, and it's a clear purification of behavior, speech, and mind, that results in an enduring non-forgetfulness, that then brings the joy, the blamelessness, virtue, brings the blamelessness, brings the joy, brings the calm, brings samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no introduction there of, oh, and then do this, and then do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like a very different flavor to it, than if you just go on your generic kind of mindfulness of breathing retreat today, where it doesn't matter where you come from, doesn't matter the level of what precepts you hold, what commitment you have to the practice, just do this practice of
[SPEAKER_01]: Of artificial calming, squinting, closing your eyes, visualizing, and the truth will reveal itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just like... Well, I bet even the mysticism of the Buddha's time, like the wrong views of the Buddha's time, they had like a mystical leaning, were not as shallow as that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Had probably more to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Had at least some form of purification implied.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, to be fair, even the Visuddhimagga assumes that you're a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't actually encourage those practices for lay people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: I apologize to Visuddhimagadhen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, a person may not realize that when they don't have unwholesome states present in their mind, that is also a work that they have to do to not let themselves fall into doing more as if, you know, there's there's kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: I always need to be purifying something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I always got to be doing something.
[SPEAKER_01]: My duty is waiting constantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a skill that needs to be developed on account of not giving in to that pressure of craving to be doing constantly and resolving doubts and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things have a reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not acting out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, there is a pressure to what?
[SPEAKER_01]: To understand or to get rid of?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or to replace discomfort with comfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: All these intentions are already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not seeing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that, you won't see, when you are actually in a wholesome state, that you don't need to do anything about.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to prevent from slipping from.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: The true, correctly practiced mindfulness, it's effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Sutta says you can't have too much of sati.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't overdo it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have too much of not forgetting about important things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said so many times, even that's corrupted today, through the same principle of, you know, people through, like, whatever, mystical learning, self-hypnotic practices, then try to read the suttas with those sort of framework glasses on, and then they see these things in the suttas that are not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Such as, mindfulness means memory, means non-forgetfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ask yourself, in the same sense, like, in a colloquial sense, what does it mean to not be forgetful?
[SPEAKER_01]: Does it mean, like, focusing on every second of my experience, day to day, watching everything in front of my eyes?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: By any stretch, like, even if you want to try to do that, in order to not forget things, you forget things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you not forget?
[SPEAKER_01]: What technique do you do when you remember?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you realize, oh, you forget, basically, when things are important to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't forget, even if you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, make them important.
[SPEAKER_01]: Make the precepts important.
[SPEAKER_01]: Make the breaking of precepts dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Make it dangerous to act out of unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feel that danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness is growing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's just how it works, as I said, in day-to-day life, in everyone's life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, non-forgetfulness is not something you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, as I said, everything that kind of becomes spiritual is allowed to mean what it doesn't mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, non-forgetfulness, mindfulness doesn't mean that anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means a special focusing satipaṭṭhāna meditation, hypnotic calming practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like... that will actually make you forget things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will make you absorb... completely absorbed and oblivious to your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said in the other talk, understanding, understanding of stuff, like in a colloquial sense, everybody knows, okay, understanding means like getting the meaning, understanding, seeing for yourself, whereby you can explain it in your own words, you can, you could sort of see it regardless of, you know, where you learned it from and stuff, you could see it for yourself and even put it in your own terms in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, when it was taken into the spiritual context, understanding doesn't mean that anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just means anything and nothing, means a novelty experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding of the now and the is-ness of the things and stuff like that, it's like, what do you understand there?
[SPEAKER_01]: But all these things are called to as understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, he develops understanding by having a special meditation experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: We haven't understood anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just went through some novelty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some novelty that you perceive through your senses, basically.